A Finding Aid to the Edwin Burrage Child Photographs, 1902-1936, in the Archives of American Art aaa.chiledwi
Archives of American Art
Edwin Burrage Child photographs
1902-1936
aaa.chiledwi
Archives of American Art
2.2 Linear feet
The photographs of painter Edwin Burrage Child measure 2.2 linear feet and date from 1902-1936. Included in this collection are original photographic prints and copy prints; 101 negatives; 59 glass plate negatives; and one folder of miscellaneous papers including a sketch by Edwin Burrage Child. Photographs depict artwork, interiors, furniture, and people.
Child, Edwin Burrage, 1868-1937
Biographical/Historical note
Edwin Burrage Child (1868-1937) was a landscape and portrait painter who lived and worked in New York City and Dorset, Vermont, and was most known for his male portraiture.
Child was born in Gouverneur, New York in 1868 to Jonathan Bush Child and Sarah Burnham. In the 1880s, Child attended Amherst College and received art lessons during the summers from artist Margaret C. Whiting (1860-1946). In 1890, he graduated from Amherst College and moved to New York City to pursue a career as an artist, becoming a student in 1891 at the Art Students League. Child's artistic debut was in 1892 at the National Academy of Design annual exhibition. From 1891 to 1895, he studied under painter, muralist, and stained-glass designer John LaFarge (1835-1910), and worked as his assistant from 1896-1901. Edwin Burrage Child then spent many years working as an illustrator and writer for leading periodicals such as Scribner's, Harper's, McClure's, and others.
As a landscape painter, Child was awarded a medal at the Louisiana Purchase Exhibition in St. Louis in 1904, and the majority of his landscapes were modeled from his summer home in Dorset, Vermont. In 1908, his focused moved to easel painting -- primarily landscapes and portraits. Child was most known for his portraits of intellectual males, with sitters including Senator Dwight M. Morrow, Governor Wilbur L. Cross of Connecticut, Professor John Dewey, and painter Ivan G. Olinsky, among many others. His work appeared in shows at the National Academy of Design and the Society of Independent Artists in New York, as well as the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, the Art Institute of Chicago, and the Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington, D. C. He also had many one-man shows over the years, primarily in New York City. In 1930, the National Gallery of Art in Washington, D. C. held an exhibition of his portraits.
Child was married to Anna Gertrude Sykes in 1894, and they had three children: Katherine E. (1895-1966), Bradford (1896-1948), and Sargent Burrage (1900-1972). Child also made furniture as a hobby and remodeled his home in Dorset Hollow, as well as Gray's Tavern, which later became the Dorset Village Public Library. Additionally, he was a frequent lecturer, speaking at colleges and universities, including Yale, Michigan State College, Columbia, City College of New York, and Massachusetts State College at Amherst. Child spent the last ten years of his life living in Dorset, Vermont, and died in 1937.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Edwin Burrage Child photographs were transferred to the Archives of American Art on June 6, 1979, from the National Collection of Fine Arts (NCFA) Library.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Glass plates are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 5 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers, but listed where they fall intellectually within the collection.
Series 1: Photographs of People and Other Subjects, circa 1908-circa 1936 (0.45 linear feet; Boxes 1, 4-5)
Series 2: Photographs of Landscapes, Buildings, and Animals, 1903-circa 1936 (0.15 linear feet; Boxes 1, 4-5)
Series 3: Photographs of Interiors, Furniture, and Lighting, circa 1902-circa 1936 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 4: Photographs of Artwork, 1902-1936 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 2-6)
Series 5: Miscellaneous Papers, circa 1930 (1 folder; Box 3)
Scope and Contents note
The photographs of Edwin Burrage Child measure 2.2 linear feet and date from 1902-1936. Included in this collection are original photographic prints and copy prints; 101 negatives; 59 glass plate negatives; and one folder of miscellaneous papers including a sketch by Edwin Burrage Child. Photographs depict artwork, interiors, furniture, and people.
Photographs of people and other subjects depict several portrait images of Edwin Burrage Child, as well as many photographs and negatives of unidentified groups and events, children, men building a log cabin structure at Child's Dorset, Vermont home, and several models for painting.
Photographs of landscapes, buildings, and animals include a series of landscape photographs of Central Park, complete with the city in the background; many images of the Dorset, Vermont landscape with Child's house and barn structures depicted; landscapes with rainclouds and lightning, also in Dorset, Vermont; and images of horses attached to carriages and wagons, and cows and sheep, as well as several images of a dead horse on the streets of a small town.
Photographs of interiors, furniture, and lighting are made up primarily of copy prints and negatives, and include images of pieces of furniture, light fixtures and sconces, as well as entire interior rooms of what is probably Child's Dorset home. Additionally, photographs of Child's studio with paintings hung on walls are also found here.
Photographs of artwork make up the bulk of the collection, with original prints, copy prints, negatives, and glass plate negatives of primarily portrait paintings by Edwin Burrage Child. Many of the original photographic prints have been annotated on the backs with descriptive information about the portrait model, where they are from, and their occupation. Some annotations contain anecdotal information about Child's interactions or experiences with the sitters, and have been written by Child's youngest son, Sargent Burrage Child. While some of the descriptive information has been identified as written by both Edwin Burrage Child and Sargent Burrage Child, some writing could not be identified. A set of glass plate negatives without prints also depicts several of Child's landscape paintings. Additionally, a dismantled photograph album contains original prints of Child's portraits of men, women, and children, as well as containing the most descriptive information of all the prints in the collection.
Miscellaneous papers contains a sketch with note by Edwin Burrage Child; a handwritten letter in pencil, on Child's stationery, by Child; a typed exhibition inventory of portraits in the Washington, D. C. exhibit, "Portraits by Edwin Burrage Child," in 1930; and a copy of the 5 x 7 glass plate negatives box that previously stored glass plate negatives.
Artists' studios--Photographs; Central Park (New York, N.Y.)--Photographs; Dorset (Vt.)--Photographs; Glass plate negatives; Photographs; Sketches
- Photographs of People and Other Subjects, circa 1908-circa 1936; Series 1; 0.45 Linear feet Boxes 1, 4-5
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are portrait images of Edwin Burrage Child over decades, Child and family in snow outside of their Dorset home, models for paintings, and men building a log cabin structure at Child's Dorset, Vermont home. Also found are unidentified groups of people depicted at events and various activities, including women riding a carousel, women and men in the woods for a picnic, walking in large groups across fields, fishing, at a graduation, in a city, and at a train station. There are also images of groups of children in a field, and a baby in a carriage and high chair. One image depicts a man in patched clothing and a bowler hat outside with a harp as tall as he is, draped in rags. Another image depicts an aproned man in front of an old storefront, behind a canvas covered horse-drawn wagon, feeding scraps to several eager dogs.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged by subject. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
  - Portrait Images of Edwin Burrage Child and Family, circa 1908-circa 1936; 9 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Portrait Images, undated; 3 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Children, 1935 June 8, undated; 16 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Baby in Chair and Stroller, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    10 glass plate negatives housed in box 5
  - Men Building Log Cabin, 1926; 14 Negatives (photographic) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Man Outdoors with Harp, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2 glass plate negatives housed in box 5
  - Group on a Picnic in the Woods, undated; 2 Negatives (photographic); 3 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Groups, Events, and Activities, undated; 72 Negatives (photographic); 3 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 9-13)
  - Groups, Events, and Activities, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Washington, D. C. Exhibit" Models, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    4 glass plate negatives housed in box 4
  - Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1930, undated; 18 Glass negatives (Box 4-5)
- Photographs of Landscapes, Buildings, and Animals, 1903-circa 1936; Series 2; 0.15 Linear feet Boxes 1, 4-5
  Found here are images of primarily the Dorset, Vermont landscape --hills, fields, streams, woods --mostly with Edwin Burrage Child's house and barns depicted. Some landscape images feature a raincloud-filled sky, and one is an image of lighting striking the top of a hill. Additionally, there are several panoramic images of Central Park, complete with city line, in New York City. There are also many images of sheep, cows, and horses, mostly bridled and hitched to wagons and carriages. Several images depict one scene of a dead horse on the side of a dirt road with town storefronts and some children and people in the background.
  - Dorset Farm and House in Winter, undated; 6 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dorset Farm and House, undated; 23 Negatives (photographic); 3 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Building with Cow and Dog, 1908 March; 1 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Building, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    1 glass plate negative housed in box 5
  - Building, undated; 1 Negatives (photographic) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - House, 1908 March; 2 Photographic prints; 5 Negatives (photographic) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - House, undated; 5 Negatives (photographic) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Model of House in Dorset, VT, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Rain Clouds on Mt" Landscape, 1903; 12 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Field/Mountains Landscape, undated; 8 Negatives (photographic) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Woods Landscape, undated; 7 Negatives (photographic) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Woods/Ground, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dorset Landscapes, undated; 2 Copy prints; 20 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
  - Dorset Landscapes with Buildings, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    4 glass plate negatives housed in box 5
  - "Landscapes", 1908 March; 14 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Central Park Landscapes, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    6 glass plate negatives housed in box 4
  - Animals, Horses and Men, undated; 5 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Animals, Dead Horse on Town Street, undated; 4 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Animals, Horses Hitched to Wagons and Carriages, undated; 10 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Animals, Cows and Sheep, undated; 5 Photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Animals, Cows, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, undated; 14 Glass negatives (Box 4-5)
- Photographs of Interiors, Furniture, and Lighting, circa 1902-circa 1936; Series 3; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Included here are images of pieces of furniture (perhaps constructed by Edwin Burrage Child), light fixtures and sconces in detail and as part of larger interior rooms, as well as several images of Child's studio with portrait paintings hung on the walls.
  This series is arranged by subject.
  - Studio with Paintings, undated; 2 Photographic prints; 8 Copy prints; 7 Negatives (photographic) (Box 1, Folder 40-41)
  - Rooms and Light Fixtures, undated; 1 Photographic prints; 43 Copy prints; 17 Negatives (photographic) (Box 1, Folder 42-47)
  - Furniture, undated; 47 Copy prints; 6 Negatives (photographic) (Box 1, Folder 48-52)
- Photographs of Artwork, 1902-1936; Series 4; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 2-6
  Included here are primarily images of Edwin Burrage Child's portrait paintings, of men, women, and children. A dismantled photograph album is also included, containing Child's portrait paintings. Many of the images have descriptive annotations identifying the portrait model, where they lived, and the nature of their primary occupation. Images within the photograph album sometimes contain more descriptive detail about the sitter. While some of the annotations were written by Edwin Burrage Child, most were written by Child's youngest son, Sargent Burrage Child, sometimes containing anecdotal information about the sitter or their relationship with Child, as well as many notes by unidentified authors. Also found here are images of Child's landscape paintings of Dorset, Vermont, only in glass plate negative format. Several of the portrait paintings were noted as "Washington, D. C. Exhibition," probably meaning they were included in Child's exhibit of work at the National Collection of Fine Arts in Washington, D. C. from February to March of 1930. One self-portrait image of Edwin Burrage Child is depicted in a photographic reproduction from "The National Cyclopedia of American Biography."
  This series is arranged by subject, with portraits grouped into portraits of men, portraits of women, and portraits of children, alphabetical by the sitter's last name when provided. The photograph album has been dismantled but kept together and in its original order. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
  - Portrait Image of Edwin Burrage Child in "The National Cyclopedia of American Biography", undated; 1 Photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Portraits of Men, Unidentified, 1915, 1930-1934, undated; 5 Copy prints; 7 Photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Portraits of Men (B), 1933, undated; 6 Photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Portraits of Men (C), 1917, 1928, undated; 6 Photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Portraits of Men (D-G), 1930, undated; 3 Copy prints; 5 Photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Portraits of Men (H-J), 1920, undated; 1 Copy prints; 8 Photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Portraits of Men (L-M), 1923, 1931-1936, undated; 3 Copy prints; 8 Photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Portraits of Men (P-R), 1925, 1934, undated; 8 Photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Portraits of Men (S), 1918-1928, undated; 1 Copy prints; 14 Photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Portraits of Men (T-W), 1930-1933; 12 Photographic prints; 1 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Portraits of Men (W), 1932, undated; 9 Photographic prints (includes 1 print of a glass plate negative); 1 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Portraits of Men, 1910, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Portraits of Men, 1918-1936, undated; 7 Negatives (photographic) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Portraits of Men, 1934; 8 Negatives (photographic) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Washington, D. C. Exhibit" Portraits of Men, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    8 glass plate negatives housed in box 4
  - Portraits of Women, Unidentified, circa 1902, 1914-1936, undated; 1 Copy prints; 11 Photographic prints (includes 1 print of a glass plate negative) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Portraits of Women (A-L), 1903, 1917-1933, undated; 3 Copy prints; 11 Photographic prints (includes 1 print of a glass plate negative) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Portraits of Women (L-S), 1913-1927, undated; 13 Photographic prints (includes 2 prints of glass plate negatives) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Portraits of Women (T-W), 1909, 1927-1931, undated; 2 Copy prints; 12 Photographic prints (includes 3 duplicate prints of glass plate negatives) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Portraits of Women, 1913-1922, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Portraits of Women, 1918, 1930, undated; 9 Negatives (photographic) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Washington, D. C. Exhibit" Portraits of Women, circa 1930 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Portraits of Children, 1908-1912, 1922, undated; 10 Photographic prints (includes 1 print of a glass plate negative) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Portraits of Children, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    1 glass plate negative housed in box 4
  - Portraits of Children, 1911, 1925; 2 Negatives (photographic) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Portraits, Photograph Album, 1902-1930, undated; 32 Photographic prints (includes 1 print of a glass plate negative) (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Landscape Paintings, Dorset, VT, 1917-1921, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    9 glass plate negatives housed in box 4
  - Glass Plate Negatives, 1910-circa 1930, undated; 34 Glass negatives (Box 4-5)
- Miscellaneous Papers, circa 1930; Series 5; 1 Folders Box 3
  Found here is a sketch with note by Edwin Burrage Child; a handwritten letter in pencil, on Child's stationery, by Child; a typed exhibition inventory of portraits in the Washington, D. C. exhibit, "Portraits by Edwin Burrage Child," at the National Collection of Fine Arts in Washington, D. C. in 1930; and a copy of the 5 x 7 glass plate negatives box that previously stored glass plate negatives.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1930, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)